{
  "reference_number": "11520",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "As long as the climate change commission is flexible to new scientific data and developments, a firm target is needed, otherwise\n progress and innovation will be slow."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": "We need to efficiently produce food, which is the primary producer of short lived gases. A target that is excessively harsh on primary\n producers will only shift production elsewhere that is less carbon efficiency, harming the businesses of primary producers in NZ,\n\n making food more expensive for those that can least afford it and leaving the void to be filled by less efficient producers."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": "We are very efficient producers of food and export over 80% of our produce. As much of our footprint is as a result of providing\n protein to different economies, this needs to be reflected in a trade balance that complements our economic strengths."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The bill should be flexible for advances in scientific knowledge, monitoring measurements and considerations towards practical\n\n changes. The commission should hold a biennial consultation process that tracks changes in meeting these targets including any\n new info that comes to hand, with any altering of targets to be consulted on by way of non-binding referenda timed with general\n\n and/or local elections in a way that minimises partisan influence."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "It is impossible to meet a target without any models of how they will be achieved. A 5-15 year time-frame is sensible for this kind of\n bill."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "It is difficult to generate scientifically based outcomes when constantly used as a political football. Any decision to alter targets should\n\n be only allowed on agreement and/or recommendation from a climate commission that is established in a manner that is both\naccountable and neutral to the government of the day."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Exceptional circumstances need to be clearly defined. Adjustments to the budget would need to made to alleviate suffering, prevent\n\nundue hardship to groups of people who are powerless to change their circumstances or adapt to new scientific knowledge and\ndevelopments. Without a definition of \"exceptional circumstances\" such a question cannot be answered."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, these considerations are sound. It is important that in the event of a decision, any disproportionate negative effects on any\n\nparticular group must be considered and mitigated in the short to medium term."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, provided appropriate considerations raised in this consultation process are incorporated."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "1. The Carbon Zero Bill needs to be transitional, not punitive. Society has been built on the basis of many practices, and people\n\nshould not be punished for actions that have become embedded due to societal norms. Any practices that need to change to meet\ntargets need to occur in consultation with affected parties and changes to such practices need to change must be fairly assisted by\n\ngovernment if they are top regulate these changes. 2. Any regulation must be considered with respect to outcomes. If regulations\nare made to achieve the outcome of minimised negative climate change, then any regulations that are found to be irrelevant or\ncounter to this outcome should be removed, and a triennial review process enacted, to be overseen by the climate commission, to\n\nalter or remove out-dated or inappropriate provisions. 3. If revenues are generated as a result of a climate commission or similar, then\nsuch revenues need to be dedicated solely to the remediation of climate change and/or assistance to those that are disadvantaged\n\nby regulation. Revenues are not to be diverted to other government activities and stern oversight should be held over the Climate\nChange Commision to ensure that revenues are not spent in a way that could perversely incentivise actions by those in the\n\ncommission. 4. Minster Shaw indicated during a public meeting that New Zealand was involved with International alliances to meet\nclimate change targets. If New Zealand is to be a world leader in climate change action, then we need a tangible voice at this table.\nWe also need to ensure that any moves made by NZ government are in keeping with and/or recognised by other nations in our trade\n\nagreements."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "These functions need to be decoupled from the political process and needs a process for appointments that removes it from political\ngerrymandering. Any appointments to the commission could be ratified by votes from the Vice-Chancellors and/or Deans of\n\nrespective schools of NZ universities."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "The ETS needs to be decoupled from the political process. Eventually, any NZ ETS needs to be linked with an international market,\nwhich can only be achieved with international agreements that do not exist at this point."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "1. The commission should have a term limit of 2 terms (3-4 year terms) to prevent a culture of feathering ones' own nest and to\nencourage refreshment of expertise."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "We are a small nation. As we do not control the actions of others in adapting to climate change, our actions cannot be guaranteed to\naffect the outcome. As such, we must be prepared for failure and advice must be sought to protect us against the effects of failure."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, provided that such functions are applied with the weight of statistical credibility and updated under an independent review\nprocess."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes. These climate change risks need to be publicised as well as the impacts of adapting to climate change and/or the impacts of\n\npreventing these changes. Any information generated as a result of this needs to be carefully handled so that it does not get\nmisinterpreted."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Any climate change legislation needs to be considered in terms of genuine human need. Humans need food, shelter, warmth and\ncommunity. Many people have become very rich on the idea of environmentalism and many people will be priced out of genuine\n\nhuman need on the basis of some environmental legislation that has been proposed. As a small country, we will not solve global\nissues while impoverishing our own population. Environmentalism is a two way street, and trading one form of crony capitalism for\n\nanother will not fix anything. When embarking on any ground-breaking legislation, always remember the law of unintended\nconsequences.\n\n\n\n\n You have elected to withhold your personal details from publication."
    }
  ]
}
